Hello friends, my name is Jai Sharma and
you are welcome to our
discussion today, so subscribe
to our channel so that you keep getting notifications of such
videos that we keep making, so
let's start,
now friends let's understand where do you get group
insurance or individual
insurance
or from where can you get it, so friends,
if you are an employee in a company, you
work in a company, then it can be your
employer because there are about 50
companies which
offer insurance to their employees, so
you get insurance from the company in which you work, it is
possible that the
company which is your company pays the
premium for the insurance you are getting from there, or it is possible
that both of you and the company have
equal contribution in it, then the contribution of both can be
there or
you can get it from the bank, you can get this group insurance from the branch where you have
your account, the branch from which you have
opened your bank account,
apart from that there are credit card companies from which  Your
credit card is running where you have an
SBI credit card or an ADFC
credit card, then these
companies also offer you a group
insurance, they design it for their customers
and then offer it to them, in
this way like
airtelhellotunes.in is doing, they have
taken a group policy for their customers, they have got it
designed as per their requirement and they
give a group policy to their customers, among
others, apart from this, suppose you
live in a society, then a society, an
entire group can get together and take a policy for itself, by
talking to a company, each one can
take a group policy for his society, in
this way many things, that is,
a group which is complete, an entire
group can get together and take a policy for itself
so that all its people in it, let's say there are
400, 500, thousand people, then it can get
them insured, let's talk about an
individual policy, then you
can get it from an agent there, the agent will tell
you  Individual policies can be given, the
terms and conditions of these policies
may be the same,
but these policies, these
group policies, people get
them designed as per their own choice,
like the employer is getting it designed for his employee as per his choice,
he
wants to give maternity cover or not, he
wants to give it after pre-registration days or he wants OPD cover, so in this
way every group, whether it is a bank getting a
policy designed for its customer
or an employer getting it done for its employee
or a credit card company getting it done
for its customer or any other,
if any big group
wants to take an insurance for itself, then it can customize its policy as per its choice,
it may have less features or it may be that
they set the features as per their choice,
but what is the matter here, all these
policies which you take as individual policies,
then these policies are pre-defined policies,
these plans are already in the market,
you can get these policies from an agent  You can
take this policy from the bank. You can take
both the policies from the bank. You can
also take a group policy. You can take an individual
policy. You can take the policy from a broker.
You can go online to Policy Bazaar on the
phone.
Wherever your source is, you will get the
policy there. Meaning, if you are
taking a policy from IC Lombard and
this is your source. If you take the policy from anywhere,
you will get the same policy there. Here, it is
different. These people design the policy according to their own choice,
so then there is a slight difference in their policies.
Now friends, let's talk
about some negatives and positives.
Friends, there are both negatives and positives.
Some are positive in group policies,
some are negative.
Similarly, there are some negatives or positives in individual policies. So, we will
talk
about both. If we talk about group
insurance, then the first option that comes is '
Not Permanent'. It is not permanent. If
you are working in a company and you
leave your job, then understand that your group
insurance is over. Similarly, if you
took a policy from a bank, if the tie-up of that bank with
that insurance company is over.  So
understand that your insurance has ended or if
you take a group policy from any other source
and if their type
ends there then your policy ends
but here this is permanent
coverage, if you have taken it for yourself then whole
life as long as you are alive as long as you
want for your family you can renew this insurance cover
regularly, you can renew this policy every year,
no
portability, this is the second negative point
which is in the group policy, you
cannot port this policy, either you
will run this policy or you will end this policy, if
you want
you cannot port this policy to any other company
but here you can port this policy, you do
not like the policy,
you feel that brother the services of this company are
not good, you
can port the policy by shifting to that company, here
you cannot port the policy, let's talk about
add-ons, so friends, here there are pre-
defined add-ons which a group
or an Apple employer which is a company can provide
for its employees or for that
group  For this, you talk to the company in advance and
add those features there.
You
cannot add any add-ons to those which are fixed. Many
add-ons are available in your policy, you
cannot add them, but here you
can add all types of add-ons. There are no
restrictions here. No
restoration. Friends, in the time limit
you get here,
you will not get the facility of restoration in the sum limit.
Meaning, the cover you have taken, for example, if it is a
cover of Rs 3 lakh or Rs 5 lakh, then whatever
you use will expire once, then
you will not be able to use it again.
But here your restoration option is
available. Many companies restore you up to 100%.
Many companies
give you the option of multiple registrations, so this is a
thing of greater benefit for you. Talking about
premium, one benefit you
get in group policy is less premium.
You get less premium here
because you have a big group. The
insurance company you are tying up with
knows this.  That brother, we are going to get a
big business from here, so in that way, the
group or the employer and the
insurance company both of them tie up,
they sit and talk, brother,
what are we offering you or what do you or the
employer or the group want,
they make a deal accordingly and select your premium,
select your policy,
so here your premium is a little
less, but here because this
policy is individual, you are designing the policy as per your requirement, you are
taking the policy as per your requirement, you are adding add-ons as per your requirement, you are
adding features as per your requirement,
so there are chances of your premium being high here
and your
premium will always be higher here than in a group policy.
No Medical:
Many times in a group policy you do not need medical
and in almost all the group policies you do
not need medical, but here
after a certain age, whether it is after 45 in some company,
50 in some company, 55 in some company
or after 60 in some company,
medical is required, so here
you get the policy without any medical
You can get the policy here only after completing the medical.
Our seventh point is non-medical not
covered. In these policies, non-
medical is not covered. Suppose the
group has already added it after talking to the company as per its wish, then it
is fine,
but if the non-medical cover is not there, then
you will have to pay here. Whatever non-medical
charges there are, which are consumer charges,
you have to pay them here.
But in this policy, you have an add-on
available. After adding it from there,
you add the non-medical rider,
then your charges are over and
you do not have to pay anything. Let's talk about
no claim bonus, then no claim bonus is
not available here. If you are
running the policy for suppose four to five years, then
you will not get any non-claim bonus. Your tenure will remain the same,
but here, if you do not take a claim, then
your sum will increase. Some company
gives you a bonus of 50%, some gives you a bonus,
so suppose if you are getting a bonus of 20%
and for 5 years  If you do not claim, then
your sum share becomes 10 lakh instead of 5 lakh
or if you have taken 10 lakh then it becomes 20
lakh instead of that, so here you
get this extra benefit, apart from that, there is
requirement on less sum share, friends, here the
time limit is limited, your
group or your employer
keeps a limited time limit for you, 1 lakh, 2
lakh, 3 lakh or maximum 5 lakh, but there is
no such limit here, you can take
as much
cover as you want as per your requirement because see, 3 to 4 lakh 5
lakh sum share is nothing, it gets exhausted in four to five days,
so our time share should
always be more, there is no
such restriction here, you can
take as much sum share as you want, you need 5 lakh, 10 lakh, 20 lakh,
50 lakh, 1 crore, 2 crore, as much
sum share as you want as per the requirement, you
can take that much here, let's talk about tax
saving, so friends, if you are an employer,  If your
employer is giving you a policy, then
you cannot get tax savings there because
whatever the employer is paying on your behalf, then
you get the tax benefit of that there,
they get the tax
benefit there, but what is there here, the tax
benefit is available to you here, if
you are taking a policy for yourself and it is
more than ₹2500000, then you
can get tax savings up to ₹5000000 there, but
what is there here, the condition here
is a little different, if you are taking a group policy
and you are paying for it yourself,
like you are paying to the bank or you are making the
payment yourself in any other group policy, then
you
get tax savings there also, but if the employer is
paying for the policy on your behalf,
then you will not get tax benefit in that, if we
talk about maternity cover, then
maternity cover can be there in both, there can be
maternity cover here, you can be
covered from the first day.  There should be a waiting period of nine months
after that there should be cover here too.
Here also the
situation in the waiting period is the same that brother,
according to the plan that the company is offering you, you get the insurance cover up
to the entire sum assured, it is possible that
somewhere you will get ₹ 55000, 225000, 0000 sum assured, so the
conditions are different in both,
whenever you take a policy, do
check it once. Talking about the claim service,
friends, you get the claim service
in both, but the
claim service that you get here is
through the agent or the broker from whom you are
taking the policy, you can get a little better claim service from where you are taking the policy online.
Here for the claim,
you will have to talk to the company directly, for example,
suppose your insurance is
from ICC Lombard, then here if you have group
insurance, then you have to talk directly to the company, there is no
one in between, so
no one will be available to help you, it is
possible that they may be available.  It may or may not be there,
but here your agent, the broker
from whom you are buying the policy, let's say
from Policy Bazaar, then
those Policy Bazaar people will
always be there for you. You can call them,
you can also do it directly to the company. So,
you will get better claim service here. Let's
talk about after-sales service. If
you need any endorsement or any change
in the policy, then you will get it
better here. Instead of here,
you will have to talk to the company directly,
you will have to email, you will have to call,
but here you can get changes done through the agent or
through Policy Bazaar. Let's
talk about pre-assisting
diseases, so friends, here you get a benefit in the
group policy that
some pre-assisted
[Music]
15. Our option is no coverage after
retirement. This can happen because when you
retire, the company's
insurance will end, so
you will not get that coverage there.
But the cover that you take here, you will continue to get it as long as
you use it, as long as you keep renewing it.
In this, it is possible that the
group policy you are taking from the bank continues to be available to
you
after the age of 60, but it is possible that the
policy with the employer may end here.
So the benefit in both is that
you can renew your individual policy as per your convenience. You
can renew it for as long as you want.
In this policy, let's talk about the waiting period in the group policy. The
waiting
period may be slightly less. There may be
no waiting period for anything,
but here there is a standard waiting period.
Whatever is your 30-day waiting period
or your 2-year
waiting period for specific diseases or your pre-
existing condition, if you keep it here, then there may be a slight difference between the
waiting period here and the waiting
period here. Now
friends, let's talk about which of the two
policies, group policy and individual
policy, is better and
which policy should we take. Friends,
we will understand this with an example.  Now suppose
you have taken a policy for 30 years
and you have run that policy for four to five years.
Now God forbid if someone falls ill
but someone gets a chronic disease
and after that your tie-up with group
insurance ends. Now
what option do you have that you can take another policy.
You take an individual policy at that time
but when you go to take it and you
tell your pre-assisting DJs there then the company does
not accept your proposal. So the biggest loss
friends is that the group policy is
not permanent, there is no way to know
when it will end, when the company will stop it,
when the employer will stop giving you the cover. So you should
always have a permanent policy and an individual
policy. If your group
policy is running, even after that you should take a
permanent individual policy
for your family. The second
option is that you get less sum assured
in the group policy but in the individual policy you
can take the sum assured as per your wish, 2
lakhs.  A sum assured of Rs 3 lakh or Rs 5 lakh is nothing.
You can get a
sum assured of Rs 5 lakh, Rs 10 lakh, Rs 20 lakh or Rs 50 lakh as per your convenience. So,
taking an individual policy instead of a group policy is considered a good option and is a
good option. Now friends, there
is an option available because suppose
you are suffering from a chronic disease, any disease that has been going on for
many years and
if the policy breaks down, then the company does
not cover you and you have to pay all its expenses
yourself. So, it is a
mandatory thing that you have to take an individual
policy. Now, if someone is running a group policy and also takes an individual policy, then
how can they take the policy in it?
Look, if you are paying the full premium of the individual policy
and here you have another
policy running, then your premium is also
going to be higher and you will not get any special cover as
brother,
you cannot use both the policies together,
so you can do one thing in it that
Suppose you have a group policy
of ₹ lakh or ₹ 5 lakh, then
in the individual policy there is an option of
deductible. When you choose the deductible option,
your premium reduces a little.
Suppose you
took out the premium from ICCI Lombard, the premium came to ₹
00 and your cover was ₹ 10 lakh
and along with that you have a policy running which is
of ₹ lakh or a group policy of ₹ lakh,
then you can do one thing in it
that you can choose the deductible option in the ICCI Lombard policy which is an
individual policy.
As soon as
you choose the deductible option,
what happens in it is that whatever claim you make, whatever
deductible you choose, be it ₹
50000, ₹ 1 lakh or ₹ lakh, then first you will have to pay that money
from your pocket or through that group policy
and the
amount above that will be borne by you from this policy which is an
individual policy.  If you get it then what will happen with it,
now suppose
look at your policy, you will
not pay in cash because if you have to pay in cash,
you do not have any policy, then you will pay the
full premium, but if
you are running a group policy, then what will happen in it,
now suppose in your
claim of ₹ lakh, whatever deductible is there of ₹ lakh or ₹ lakh,
first that claim will be taken
from your group policy, secondly, the
claim above, if suppose a
claim of more than 2 lakhs comes, then that will be taken from your main
policy which is an individual policy,
now what is one advantage in this,
suppose in future
both your policies are running and
both the policies are running for you together for 5 years or 6 years, then due to
some reason if the group
policy ends, the tie-up of the group ends,
then the detachable option which is given to you
in the main policy, the
detachable option in the individual policy,
you can remove that detachable option from there
and you can cancel
that policy by paying a little extra premium  If you
can continue, what will happen is that your
premium is also saved by it, your coverage is also
saved from both sides, you have a group policy
running, you have an individual policy
running, your premium is also going down,
but if such a situation arises that your
group policy or employer policy
is removed, then you can
remove your deductible option from that individual policy and continue that policy
completely, so
after removing the deductible of ₹ lakhs of your coverage that you have taken, you
get complete coverage and all the
diseases that you have already had, all those
diseases are covered in it,
so friends, this was our today's video
regarding group and individual policy,
what is the difference between the two, I have
told you both, so you always have to keep in mind
that you have to take the policy individually,
even if
you have to take it by deducting, but you have to
keep an individual policy together, so
friends, how did you like this video, do
tell us, like our video and
subscribe to our channel  If
you think that this video we have made can be
helpful for someone, then
you can also share this video in your group.
Thank you.